We're going to look at
logic in this first
part of the course.
And the first thing
to do is to work
out what logic might be.
Philosophers are worried about
that ever since the
ancient Greeks,
one way of looking at
the modern view of logic
from the point of view of a
philosopher is read as book,
Language, Truth, and Logic.
If you start worrying,
what does all this mean?
How do we fit with the way
we speak with the world?
And you start thinking
philosophically, get that book,
you'll find it second hand all
over the place because
it's been around for
a long time and many millions of
students have ready
Language, Truth, and Logic.
We're not going to take
things quite in that order.
We're going to start with truth,
very simple world where
we know what's true.
And then we'll do some
logic with that world.
With worlds like that,
without talking about
language for the moment.
Forget everything you
may have learned about
Boolean algebra or logic,
and just think about things
and the way they behave.
Now, why are we
doing this course?
Part of it is because there
is some technical stuff
that you need in
doing informatics,
computation, writing
programs, designing
machines that some technical
logic that you need.
But over and above that,
we'll see that when
we say things in
English, it's often imprecise.
So one of the things you
should learn from this course
is where some of those
imprecisions may lie.
And you may learn to actually
say things more clearly,
more precisely.
And that will really help you
because often not
just in this course,
but throughout your course.
You'll be asked for
a definition of
something or to explain
why one thing follows
from another.
And although you won't use
formal logic to do that,
some of the ways of expressing
yourself that you learn
through the formal logic.
To do that, you should
learn from this
course and skills a
clear, concise,
unambiguous communication.
As I said, we're going to
look at very simple thing.
Three, we had a big blue
triangle and the small red this.
We're going to talk about
finite universities,
so we call it the universe.
It's everything. But that just
means it's everything
we're going to talk about.
So our universe is
going to be very
small with just a few things.
And we'll start off
with this example.
Nine shapes.
How would you describe
those shapes?
Previous slide was a
hint. What's this?
It's a small blue triangle, okay,
and this is a large green disc,
local disks and triangles.
Here are some things we might
want to say about those things.
Which of those are true and
which of them are false?
Cause the video for a moment
and decide for yourself.
Then you won't have any problem
deciding which of those are
true and which are false.
Can somebody give me an
example of a false 1 second 1,
every small triangle is read.
Why that's not true,
because there's a
blue small triangle.
I hope you can all.
Answer those questions.
What we're going to do
today is to see how we
might program up in Haskell
to answer these questions.
Before we get to that,
we'll talk a little bit about
how we represent the world.
So the first thing we do is
to give names for the things.
So I've labeled them RFT U,
V, W, X, Y, Z.
Okay, they've got
names and the names
mean nothing when we
use names for things.
It's not the same as saying
the small green triangle.
It's just a name for that thing.
And one way of describing this
world in Haskell would be,
first of all, to introduce
an enumerated type.
That means we just
list what's in it.
That's what enumerated means.
So this type thing has objects R,
S, T, U, V,
W X, Y, Z.
And if I just write it
like that in Haskell,
that gives me a new
type called thing.
And it gives me
those nine things.
And then I need to first of
all say thorough colors.
We have red, blue, and
green that reshapes.
We have disks and
triangles and their sizes.
We have begun small.
So we've just introduced
three more types.
The same way they're
enumerated types.
We just say, here's a thing
and it's got these things.
And basically those
are their names.
There's no meaning to
red or blue or green.
It's just a name for
something that we're
going to call a color.
What we're then going to do
is to define some functions.
You see these objects we've
introduced all have
capital letters.
They're what's
called constructors.
When I write them down,
I'm writing down a
name for something.
When I write
something that begins
with a lowercase letter,
then that's a variable
which could take values.
Here we're going
to define color to
be a function from
things to colors,
and shape, to be a function
from things to shapes and sizes,
to be a function from
things to the sizes.
So how would we define
that? Very easily?
We just list things.
So for instance, I'll do color.
It's the most complicated one.
The function, the
function from things,
the colors, the types in
Haskell are all important.
They tell you what
you can do with
things and they can tell
you what things do.
So always look at the type.
Color is a function of
type, thing to color.
Shall I say that the color
of our color is green,
the color of S is green,
the color is blue.
This just lists all the things
and says what colors they have.
One thing I haven't
said about logic
is we don't want a logic
for talking about shapes.
We don't want the logic
for talking about animals.
We want logic that
works when we don't even know
what we're talking about.
Sometimes you don't know
what you're talking about,
but at least you can reason
if you know some facts.
You can make deductions
logically without
knowing the details of what
these things are,
how they're made.
And that's called abstraction.
You've come away and you just
look at some properties and
you reason about them without
necessarily knowing
everything else.
The word logic comes from logos.
Ology is used for nouns
denoting study of something.
What we want to do is throw
away the things that we're
reasoning about and just
talk about what's left.
So how do we do that?
We look again at this model.
Instead of saying, what's
the color of this,
we're going to say
this has the property.
It is blue, or that has
the property. It is red.
That has the property.
It's a desk. Why would
we want to do that?
What we do is we
take the universe.
How am I going to define
in Haskell predicates,
all of them are going to be
functions from things to Boolean.
So these properties icon
assertive things and they're
either true or false.
And when I gave a theme
to this function,
I'll get an answer,
true or false.
So if I say k is red
and apply it to you,
you would expect to get true.
If I say is blue and
apply it to you,
you would expect to get thoughts.
Instead of three features,
color, shape, and size.
I've now got more than doubled
the number of properties.
But the nice thing is that only
has properties have
the same type.
So we work with those things.
We're not doing something
that we'd have to invent
over again when we wanted to
talk about different features.
We could target, is it
fairly or not fairy?
And we'd have to introduce
a whole new type
for talking about that.
It's much simpler from the
point of view of uniformity.
If we just talk about
these predicates.
And we can define predicates.
Here. We want is this, It's true.
It's true of you.
It's true of why it's true of Z.
And then the next line,
this line here, we
put an underscore.
The underscore is a pattern
that matches anything.
If we have a
constructor like are,
we can use it in a pattern when
we're defining a function.
So we can use it as a name.
And we can say this function on
this value gives this answer.
Is disk r equals true.
Says when I apply the function is
this thing I've got, is this one.
The answer is true. If it's
this one, then the
answer is true.
If it's this one,
than the answer is
true if it's this one,
10-year ancestry.
And when that
function is executed,
that's certainly the effect.
The effect is the same as if we
test this and see if it's
our test this and
see if it's you.
And when we do get one,
let it is we give the answer.
When we get down here.
It says, no matter what else you
have that matches this pattern.
And the answer is false.
So it's called a wildcard.
It's an underscore and it's
actually a lot of typing.
If you use the underscore
at the beginning.
We'll use the underscore
as soon as you can,
test these things in order
going through the clauses.
So you put them in
the right order.
You very seldom want an
underscore higher up.
The logic is, it
tells me this answer,
it tells me the sounds.
And if it gets beyond
all of those outside,
its false, what are we going
to do about is triangle?
In order to define is triangle,
we can just define it by
saying whatever we have.
It's a triangle.
If it's not a disk.
Now recall the types of these
was given on early a page.
Normally your prototypes
right next to them.
So you sort of have
that in your head.
Haskell doesn't require
you to declare the types,
but it's very good
to declare the types
because that tells Haskell
what you think
you're trying to do.
Haskell will check when
you write your definition.
And if it doesn't match
the type you want
it, it'll tell you.
If it doesn't match
the type you wanted.
There are two things that
could have happened.
You might have done
what you wanted to do,
but you hadn't thought
about it, Right?
You hadn't really
thought the type out.
So that helps you think about
what's really going on.
Or you may have
implemented it wrong
and it's much easier to
find out now the much later when
you run something and find
it has the wrong type.
So Haskell is strongly typed
and it will always
work counter type.
But it'll check if
you say this is
the type I intend to do it,
we'll do the check for you
and that's really useful.
Here. We have not,
not in Haskell is a function
from Booleans to Booleans.
Notice of type bool,
arrow bool, and Booleans
will be very important.
In this part of this course.
There introduce
Sprint the libraries
or you don't need to do it.
They're introduced
by a declaration.
An enumerated type bowl
is either false or true.
Data Ux equals false or true.
And then we have a
number of functions.
There are many
more, but these are
the ones we'll focus
on for the moment.
When we have identifier's
like ampersand,
ampersand that and end symbol.
We can use them as
infix is in the same
way as we say a plus B.
In logic we can say,
and in Haskell,
we can say a and B
to get the result.
If we put brackets around them,
they turn back into
normal functions.
This is, and this is,
OR, this is not.
And when we're talking
mathematically,
we will use these symbols.
True, false, not, and,
and or, which are infix
is like plus and times.
These symbols for true and false.
In mathematics, we
have true there.
But it's the top element.
And we have false here and
it's a bottom element.
So think of this symbolism as
also telling you true is up
there and false is down here.
Later, see how to
use that in doing
some computations where
we draw pictures.
And by looking at the pictures,
we can work out
things about pelagic.
Now we can go on to is read
thoroughly to read
things that we've done
that is blue, done that,
then we can be a little
bit more creative about
is green if it's not
either red or blue.
So we can code these kinds of
things very easily in Haskell,
precise, I've chosen to do
the small ones first because
there's a few fewer of them.
So I've said is small
and then it is big,
is not, is small.
Now we're going to go and
look at some comprehensions.
You should by now have
done some comprehension.
This is a comprehension,
does a generator there.
When I defined the
type for thing,
I also defined a list
of all the things and
called it things.
So we have a list that
contains every thing, right?
And that is called things.
So if I take x from that
list of all things,
and then I have two gods,
is red, is triangle.
This is a way of producing a
list of the red triangles.
And if I run it, this prompt here
is intended to mean when I put
this into the interpreter,
here's the result
below that I get out.
Okay, so when I start with
that greater than sign,
it means this is something
I've put in the interpreter.
And the next line
will be its output.
I put in this comprehension and I
get out v as a singleton list.
This is the list
of red triangles.
If I take small triangle,
we should get S x v as v x.
Same thing. It doesn't
matter which order.
When we're doing the computation
will normally be using lists
to represent
collections of things.
But when we're looking at the
mathematics that goes with it,
will normally be thinking
about the set of things.
If you have one set of things,
you can put them in many
different orders in the list.
When we're thinking
of them as sets,
we don't care what
order they go in.
So small triangles, big
triangle's, small disks.
We can do all of those as well
as having these two gods.
We can do the same
thing by saying,
is red and this
triangle as the god.
Okay? So whereas before I had to,
God's separated by a comma.
Now I have one god
which is made by taking the
end of those two conditions,
the conjunction of
those two conditions.
So this gives the same answers
as what we had before.
When we do that comma,
it behaves like an n.
If we put an all that,
then we get something
quite different.
If we get the things that
are either red or triangles,
then we get all the triangles and
all the red things. Let
me write it like this.
It doesn't duplicate them.
It says is it red?
Is it a triangle if it's
either gonna put it in.
So that's another
way of using this.
If you want to get things
that are small or desks.
For instance, how are we going to
say every red triangle is
small when this property holds
for every thing where you've
got a finite universe.
So to say it holds
for everything,
is to say it holds for
this one and this one,
and this one, we
just list the things
we want and check that it holds,
a property holds for everything.
If it holds for in this instance,
R and S and T,
and u and v and w
and x and y and z.
Or if I'd taken
small red triangles,
it would be if it holds for v,
because there's only
one small red triangle.
Similarly, if I want to say
a property holds for something,
it's got to hold either
R or S or T. So when we
do a string of Ns,
we're saying every.
And when we do a string
of O's were saying sum.
So we're still trying to answer
his questions and see whether,
for instance, a red
triangle is small.
Here we're picking
out the red triangles
here instead of just
giving X, I give x.
And whether x is small.
So what I get here
is v and it's true.
So we could look at that and say,
oh yes, every red
triangle is small.
We could look at this and say,
what about small triangles?
Are they read?
It's not true that every
small triangle is read.
Is it true that some
small triangle is red?
Yes, because there's
a true in here.
If all of these are true,
then it's true for everyone.
If at least one of them is true,
then it's true for some.
Now we're going to get Haskell to
do that computation for us.
We don't really need to know
which thing we're talking about.
All we need is to know for
each one whether it's small.
So I take the red triangles,
I see if it's small,
and I take the end of that.
So the end of the is red
for the small triangles,
is false and is
giving us every and,
or is giving us some.
We'll come back to
the sort of argument.
Now is the point that I wanted
to get to in this lecture.
This is what I want you to
take away from this lecture,
not, not the venn diagram.
What I want you to take away is
that instead of
looking at features,
we will look at predicates.
When we look at predicates,
we can use Boolean logic to say
things like this and this,
not this, this, all this.
Okay? We can do those.
That when we look at
our universe and we
want to say that something's
true for everything,
then we just take the value for
each thing and add them together.
And if we get a true,
it's true for everything.
We get a false. It's not
true for everything.
And where we want to say
it's true for something,
we take all of these things
and we owe them together.
And if at least one
of them is true,
we'll get a true That comes out.
And there is some,
otherwise, there are none.
So it's not true that
sum has this property.