Hello, I'm Michael
form and this is
the first video in
the computation and logic
stream of implant a,
The University of Edinburgh.
And we're going to start
right at the beginning.
Looking at binary data.
Informatics is the study
of systems that store,
process and communicate
information.
We're going to look at
that in some detail,
but we're going to
keep it simple.
Even simple systems can have
quite complex behaviors.
We're going to begin by
asking, what is information.
We're going to find the
simplest answer we can imagine.
And then study that.
We go to the dictionary.
We find that information
is knowledge
communicated concerning
some particular fact,
subject or event.
That of which one
is the prized or
told intelligence or news.
So knowledge communicated
is information.
And information is about
some particular fact,
subject or event.
It's something we
can be told learn.
So we can get it from
sensors from other people.
We see in 1387 already the
mention of information.
So this is not a new concept.
It's very old concept,
but we're looking at it
in a very new context,
in a historical sense.
So that's already
Knowledge communicated.
In 1793. There's talk of a
very considerable information.
So this introduces the
idea that we can have
more or less information.
And as I said,
we're going to look
at the simplest example.
It turns out there are
items of information
that are indivisible,
bits of information that are
the smallest possible amount of
information you can get
and will come to them.
And that's what we'll
study to start with.
Then we have in 1852 to use a.
Similarly, the brain may be
likened to Great Central
Telegraph Office,
to which the wires,
nerves convey the information
from all parts of the body.
So here we have the idea that
information in nerves and
information traveling along
wires are both similar.
And of course nowadays
we have information
travelling on nerves just
as they did in 1852.
But the information
traveling along wires is a
lot more sophisticated
than it was in 1852.
In 1927, we have the
grapevine system,
whereby information travels very
rapidly through the length and
breadth of the underworld.
Nowadays, we have the
internet through which
information travels
very rapidly through
the length and breadth
of the underworld.
We not only have the,
the web, we have the dark web.
That's not a new thing,
that's an old thing.
That information can be misused,
can be for good or for evil.
I went to Google and search
for examples of information.
And this is what I found
is one of the many,
many, many things
that Google returned.
Examples of
information we collect
and analyze times, places,
events, your activities,
details of your hardware,
details of your connection.
When they take your data,
they take all these
sorts of information,
pictures, numbers,
sounds, and so on.
And convert them into
computer data in the
form of zeros and ones.
And we're going to look in
slightly more detail
at that process of
taking information and converting
it into zeros and ones.
So information for us is going to
be about answers to questions,
who, what, where, when,
why, and how,
questions and answers.
And we're going to
see how answers,
the questions can be broken
down into zeros and ones.
As I said, our motto
is to keep it simple.
Keep it simple. Principle states
that most systems work best.
If they kept simple,
rather them made complicated.
And that's normally applied
as a principle of
practical engineering.
But it's also a
very good principle
of theoretical investigation.
We're going to look for
simple examples and
examine them in detail.
We're going to look
at simple questions.
Simple questions are questions
that have simple answers.
So the first simplification
will look at
is that every question
gets announcer.
So there is at least one
will eliminate questions
with no answers or questions that
don't give you announcer,
We assume that the answer
comes within a finite time,
then we want questions
that are not fuzzy.
We don't want questions where
the answer is vague or imprecise.
We want a question that
gives a precise answer.
And we're going to actually make
it even simpler than that.
We're going to look at
questions that only have
a finite number of
possible answers.
And to keep simplifying,
we've eliminated
questions with 0 answers,
questions with one. I'll answer.
Our big, uninteresting.
They're not totally useless,
but they are not particularly
interesting questions with
two ounces or the first
interesting case of a question.
So the simplest
question we can think
of is a question
that has two ounces.
That leads us to binary data.
We can represent the two answers
is zeros and ones, yeses and nos,
all sorts of different ways
of naming the alternatives.
But the key thing is,
we will have questions
that always give
an answer and there are
only two possible answers,
yes or no, will use
various names and various
notations for the answers.
We can think of a
tick and across,
such as I might put on
an exam at the end
of the semester.
We have up and down.
We have true and false,
which will normally focus on.
And then we have some
symbols that we will use.
So we use T for true.
And this symbol, which
is an upside down T
for false falsity is
truth stood on its head.
And we give names
to these symbols.
This is top and bottom.
And that ordering,
that top is above
bottom will be very
useful in our
investigations later on.
When we're thinking like
engineers will
often use zeros and
ones 0 for false
and one for true.
But it doesn't really matter
what the names of these on.
It does matter that
we know which one
is true and which one is false.
And we swap them over,
we change the world entirely.
So that's going to take us to
an investigation in
the next video of how
we can talk about general
things using yes-no questions.
In this video, we
introduce the idea of
information as a
kind of thing that
is given by the
answer to a question.
Then we looked at
simple questions
which always given out,
sir, but only have finite
in many possible answers.
And then we looked at
questions with binary answers
and identified those as the
simplest possible questions.