Hello. In this video,
we're going to look
at the universe.
It's a very small universe,
not like Tommy's universe,
which had the Earth is the center
that we're not going
to have the earth,
we just have a few
imaginary things.
Here's our universe, red, blue,
an NBA, triangles and
desks, which are small.
And some which a
launch nine things.
So here we have the
small blue triangle.
And here we have
a big Amber disc.
Here we have some
statements we wanted
to make about these things,
some of which will be true
and some of which will be false.
Every red triangle is small.
Is that true or false?
Every small triangle is read.
Some big triangle is amber.
Some small disk is read.
No red thing is blue.
I want you to work out which
of these statements is true,
which is false, shouldn't
take you very long.
Every red triangle is
small. What do we do?
We find the red triangles
and we see that
this one is small and that's
the only red triangle.
So every red triangle is small.
Every small triangle
is red, is not true.
How can we see that?
Because we can
produce a small triangle.
She's not read. And we go on
similarly with the others.
I'll leave you with those
questions for the moment.
And we'll return to this
problem in the next video.
What I want you to do
in the meantime is
to work out the answers
to these questions,
but also to try and think.
What's the general way of
explaining those answers?
How can we explain
what it means for each
of these statements
to be true or false?