Welcome to Edinburgh.
I'm one of the lecturers on
the Informatics 1A course.
This may be the first video
you've seen for this course.
So let's start with the beginning.
I'm Michael Fourman,
Philip Wadler's
the other Lecturer.
I'll be with you for
the computation and logic
part of the course.
And Philip will be
teaching the Haskell.
But occasionally, I will be --
more than occasionally,
quite often, I will
be using Haskell
and you will be using Haskell
in the logic part of the course.
And sometimes Philip
will be talking
about logic as a tool for
reasoning about programs.
So both things will happen.
What I want to do today is not
do any of the technical stuff,
but to cover a part of
the wider context,
things you should bear in
mind throughout your
time at Edinburgh.
And the first one is
that informatics is not
just a bit of
theory that you can do that's
separate from the world.
It's become very apparent that
things like the
Internet are changing
the way society
works, are changing
the way democracy works,
are changing the
way commerce works.
So whenever you are
doing your informatics,
you will also need to be
thinking about what are
the possible effects of
the things you're
doing and the ethical,
legal, economic,
organisational,
and social issues that
affect what you do.
You need to bear in mind that
technology can be
used and misused.
So I'll just raise that
to plant the idea in
your heads and you should
think of that often,
but don't let it
distract you too much
from also thinking about getting
on with understanding, and the theory,
and having the fun
of the practice.
Those things can happen as well.
There is an immediate issue
that I also want to raise,
which is really
illustrated by this slide.
And you can find
plenty of slides like
this or more
up-to-date news about
the same things. In the
workplace in general,
but in IT, in particular,
there is a gender pay gap.
If you look in IT, there's
also a participation
gap based on gender.
Certainly in Europe and
the UK and the USA,
the number of women
in the subject
is much smaller than
it should be: it's not
because women are not capable,
it's because societal
issues stop them or
discourage them from
participating in this area.
Now, we're lucky there are plenty
of women in informatics
at Edinburgh, but we are not as
lucky as we might be because
there aren't enough.
Just as with almost
every other university
in the western world.
What we want to do is to
make sure that your time
here is not contributing
to those problems.
If you look at the big companies,
many of them have programs
designed to attract more women.
But generally, it's
been identified that
one of the reasons
women don't like
to participate is because
of the normally unconscious
attitudes of their peers,
of the people who
are in the industry.
So what we want to
make sure of is that
those forces aren't dissuading
our students from continue
with that degree,
continue with careers
after the degrees,
or even coming here
in the first place.
So right from the beginning,
we want you to be aware
of the ways you
interact with each
other and try taking
this Harvard Test
for implicit bias:
you will find that you
get surprising results.
I know of no one who's taken
this and thought about it,
who hasn't been surprised at
their own biases being
more than they would have
expected if you just ask them.
So we want to ensure our
graduates learn to change,
try reading that...
try watching that video,
and think about these
things. You will be,
and I'll talk about this
more later in this lecture,
we'll be interacting
with each other.
When you interact
with each other,
be aware of the fact
that we are all
subject to implicit biases,
and try to make sure that
those don't affect the ways
you interact with each other.
If you experience problems,
by all means bring it to
our attention because we'd
like to address these things.
But much the best
way of dealing with
this is for everyone
on the course to
understand the issues and talk
about them openly
and address them.
So in your interactions,
and your interactions
will largely be online,
which is even more difficult,
I think, than face-to-face,
don't be exclusive.
One of the benefits of being at
the university or being
in this cohort of
people who were studying at
Edinburgh is that
you get exposed to
a wide variety of people from
a wide variety of backgrounds,
who are all very smart.
And the more you can
benefit from being exposed
to people who are not like you,
the more, the more good you'll
get out of the experience.
So don't be exclusive.
Mix with people who
are not like you.
Make sure that you're
not implicitly or
subconsciously viewing them in
a way that the facts
don't merit,
they're all smart, they wouldn't
be here if they weren't,
just as you wouldn't.
Develop for yourselves,
a core value system.
We need to treat each other
fairly and respect each other.
And change the way
you look at things.
When you are interacting
with other people,
try and be aware of
the possibility of,
in fact, the prevalence
of implicit bias.
Don't be the person who
excludes others in the group.
Recognize your
unconscious actions.
And if you are feeling
you're excluded,
don't let that happen.
Don't let them hold
you or others back.
One of the skills
you'll learn from
this course is to talk.
You might think you
can talk very well
already and I'm sure you can.
But to talk concisely and precisely
about technical things.
You need to learn these skills
because often when
we're talking about
programs or designs or systems,
we need to make quite
subtle distinctions.
And natural language
is often very
bad at making those distinctions.
So you will learn about
formal languages a bit in this
course and more later on.
But you will also learn to
use your natural languages,
more precisely.
And one of the ways you
will do that is by working
with other people and
exercising those skills,
talking to each other
about what goes on.
So you should do that as much as
possible. When you
have a problem,
Don't think you're thick.
Don't think, oh gosh,
I can't do this. Think...
who can I talk to about this
so we can work it out together?
And you will normally
find that there are
plenty of people around.
And talking together helps
both of you to learn something.
So do that as much as
possible or almost
as much as possible.
The one exception is there's
some assessed work
in this course.
And when you submit
assessed work,
it should reflect your abilities.
And basically, it should be
your work. In preparing
to do the assessed work,
of course, you should
talk with each other.
But when it comes down to
what you're going to submit,
you should make sure it's your
work and submit that.
So... Informatics, we use
this word informatics.
Why? Why not just
computer science or
AI or computer engineering?
And the answer is
because informatics is
in some ways broader
than any one of those.
It turns out that when
you're studying hardware,
when you're studying
hot software,
human-computer
human-computer interaction,
when you're studying
artificial intelligence,
in all those different
aspects of the study,
you're thinking about information
and
the ways in which it is sensed,
stored, processed,
communicated, and so on.
So when we say Informatics,
we try and be very broad.
We're interested in the way
the brain works as a computer.
We're interested in
the way societies
communicate with societies --
and ants communicate,
we'd have people working
on those kinds of things.
We're interested in information.
And it turns out that
the basic mathematics
and theory is a,
is a foundation across
all of those subjects.
So we talk about software,
hardware, people and things,
and they all sense,
store, process, and
communicate information.
Now, if you look in
our course handbook
for the later years,
you'll see that there
are many, many subjects,
many many courses: block chains,
bioinformatics,
computer algebra, cryptography,
machine translation.
Lots of things! If you come
a bit earlier in the years,
algorithms and data structures,
reasoning and agents,
object-oriented programming,
software engineering.
And if you come down to
the very early years,
we find things like
computation and logic
and functional programming,
which are the subject
of this course.
And they're here
in the first year
because the things you will learn
now will help you in all of
those different subjects.
There are many subjects.
It's impossible that any of
you can take all of them
because there are too many.
So that's another advantage
of talking to other people.
Because if they're doing
something slightly
different and you need a bit of
knowledge about something
where you're not taking
that deep course in
that particular subject because
you're developing
yourself elsewhere,
you'll still find people
around who know about
that stuff and can help
you if you need help.
So we're going to do
something foundational.
It's going to prepare you
for the rest of the course,
the rest of your degree.
And we have a motto for this course,
which is Keep It Simple.
The second S sometimes
is said Stupid,
but it may just be Small
or it may be Satisfying.
You can make your own second S,
but keep it Simple.
And in this course, we really will be
exploring
small examples.
But they nevertheless
are very interesting.
And in fact, some of the
things that we're exploring,
most of the things
we're exploring, are
relatively recent inventions in
the history of human thought.
Even though some of
the problems that are
addressing date
back to the Greeks.
and before. You're
going to learn to use
a general purpose programming
language, Haskell.
It's very well adapted in
particular for this course,
for a couple of reasons.
A logic that allows us to reason
about information,
propositional logic.
And this is the simplest
logic you can think of.
But it also turns out to
be remarkably complex
in some strict computational sense.
You'll learn about some
very simple machines
that aren't as
complicated as the machines
that we like to
think we're using,
but actually really are
as complicated as any
machine we might build.
So we like to think about
some machines that might
have infinite memory,
whereas we're going to study
machines that don't
have infinite memory.
Okay? We're going to find that
even these simple systems
have quite complex behaviors.
And we're going to talk about
these systems in a
very abstract way.
That is, we're not
building a machine
when we talk about machines,
we're building a
model of machine.
And the way we get the simplicity
is by forgetting about
many of the physical
aspects that make
it difficult to build
a real computer.
And think about an
idealized computer that
we can study with
paper and pencil.
We'll then find
things get a bit too
complicated sometimes
for paper and pencil,
so we'll also use Haskell as
a tool to help us
study the logic.
So we get this very introverted
recursive nature of
the subject that we use
the computers to help us
understand computers.
Okay. That's all I wanted to
say to you in this video.
And the next ones will include
some technical material that
I hope you'll find
more interesting,
but don't forget to look
after each other,
respect each other.
Don't forget to talk
about your work.
And don't forget when
you submit assessed work,
make sure it's your own.
Thank you!