In this video, we're
going to look at how to
code up our simple
universe in Haskell.
This is the universe we had with
nine triangles and
desks, various colors.
And we made statements
about them.
So we've discussed that
what we're going to do
now is to code it in Haskell.
So we can write queries in
Haskell corresponding
to those statements.
The first thing we
have to do is to look
at describing the universe.
In Haskell, everything
has a type.
We don't want to
describe the universe by
coding it up with integers
or something like that.
We want to just talk about
the things in the universe.
So what we're going
to do is to introduce
their names as elements
of a special type that we
create out of nowhere.
Then we'll describe
their properties
by defining functions in Haskell.
So the first thing we
have to do is to create
a type with nine things
whose names are RST U,
V, W, X, Y, Z.
That's done very
simply in Haskell,
we simply make a
data declaration.
This is just about the simplest
data declaration we can make.
We say a thing is either R or S,
or T, or U,
or V, or W, or X, or Y or Z.
What that does, that declaration
creates a type called thing.
And there are nine values of
type thing and their
names are RST U,
V, W, X, Y, Z.
We can take things and
put them in a list,
for instance, as we can with
objects of any given type.
So we can define the
list of things to be R,
S, T, U, V, W, X,
Y, Z, all put analyst.
And that's a list of length
nine containing all the
things in our universe.
The first description
we're going to give of
the universe is going to be in
terms of the features
of the things,
have color, shape, and size.
To deal with colors,
shapes and sizes will
introduce three more types.
A type color, type,
shape, and a type size.
Again, we'll use one of
these enumerated type definitions
for each of these types.
So we're just creating in
Haskell types for the things
you want to talk about.
We talk about these three colors.
We could add more if we wanted to
have a bigger palette of colors,
we talk about these two shapes.
Again, we could have more.
And we talk about these
two sizes, big and small.
The features will be functions
from things to colors,
from things to shape,
things to size.
We're going to define
a function color such
that the color of t,
for instance, is blue.
While the color of u will be red.
We can do this simply in Haskell.
We say data color is
red or blue or green.
We're defining a function
colour of type, thing to color.
And we just look,
color of R is green.
So we write that down.
Color of S is green,
colour of T is blue, and so on.
We just list or
enumerate these clauses.
And that creates a color in
Haskell that gives everything
the correct color.
If we've defined it correctly.
We could give similar definitions
for shape and size for
each of the objects.
So we'd have then our
type thing or type color,
our type shape, type size.
We'd have features which are
functions from things to colors,
things to shapes,
things, thesises.
And if we start to describe
any real situation in this way,
we get an awful lot of
different types and we have
to treat them all differently.
So instead of doing that,
we're going to describe
things in the universe,
introducing predicates
that describe
the properties that they have.
So for instance, it is
true that T is blue.
It is true that zed is blue,
but it's false that u is blue.
We can describe all of
our features by giving
predicates instead.
And that's a lot more uniform.
We will use the same
kind of thing to
describe the predicate
of being read,
the predicate of being a disc,
and the predicate of being large.
So the large red disc would
satisfy all three of
those predicates.
On the other hand, it's false.
For instance, that
zed is a triangle.
It's false that r is big and
it's false that u is small.
So we'll define what
things are big,
what things are small.
Not by saying we have a function
which gives the feature,
but by saying we
have a predicate,
which tells us a
predicate is a function
from things in the universe
to the Boolean values.
And we can say that very
succinctly in Haskell,
we say type predicate
equals thing arrows bool.
Thereafter we can use predicate.
When we're talking
about that type,
bool is the boolean type.
And in fact, BU,
although it's introduced
in the prelude,
is actually defined in terms
of constructors false and true.
Once we got this
type abbreviation,
we say predicate to
mean thing arrows bool.
Then we can use it.
As before, we declare
the data type thing as
an enumerated type.
We have the data type of things.
We have a list of all things.
We're going to
define a predicate.
The thing arrows bow.
Then we're going to
define predicates.
Is red, is blue, is green,
is disk, is triangle,
is small, and is big.
And all of those
will be predicates.
We define those predicates.
This is just repeated
up here and we wouldn't
repeat it to cause
in a Haskell file.
But it's just to remind
us that the context,
we have a data type thing.
It has all these values
and those are the
only values we have.
So in order to say whether
something's a disc,
we can say, well it's a disk
if it's r or u, or y or z.
So is disc R is true,
is this, U is true,
is this Y is true,
and is disk Zed is true
for anything else.
And that's what this
wildcard underscore does
for anything else
is disk is false.
So we only need to mention
these four disks and
then say that nothing
else is a disk.
Then we can say that
something is a triangle.
It's not a desk.
And remember, predicates
are functions.
So to define what
is triangle means,
we say is triangle of x.
The value of that is
the negation of the
value of is disk of X.
So we check whether it's a desk.
If that's true, then
it's not a triangle.
If that's false, then
it is a triangle.
These declarations show you
an important feature of Haskell.
And if you haven't seen the
Haskell thread already,
I'll just pointed out briefly,
when we introduce these
values in a data declaration,
we use capital letters.
These are things
called constructors.
They're not variables then
names for things in the
type we've introduced.
We can use those
constructors as patterns.
Here the pattern is very simple.
It just says if it's r,
do this, if it's you
do this, and so on.
We can use those as patterns
when we're defining
functions by saying what value
they have for a given variable,
then that variable always
starts with a lowercase.
So is triangle, X is not
the value of is disk of X.
This X could be any one of these.
Whereas in these declarations,
These are just stands for that.
We have operations in
Haskell on Booleans.
These operations correspond to
the Boolean operations
we've already talked about.
We have constants true and
false because the Boolean type
was introduced as
an enumerated type
with the value is false and true.
Then we have infix
functions and or,
which correspond to the
logical AND logical OR.
And we have negation or not
which corresponds to not.
This not goes from bowl to BU.
Will also need to introduce
the negation on predicates,
which we'll do shortly.
Continuing with our example,
we can also define
the predicate is
read by saying we have
these two red things.
It's true for these,
it's false for these,
false for anything else is blue,
is true for these
three blue things.
And false for anything else.
When we come to is green,
we can make another function
definition to define
this in terms of the values
of his red and blue.
We can do a similar thing
with is small and is big.
We list the small things,
are S, v and x are small.
Anything else is not small.
Something's big.
If it's not small.
This is correct.
But no real Haskell programmer
would write it this way.
They would write not dot is
small.com two functions is small.
Function from things to Booleans.
Not is a function from
Booleans to booleans.
And when we compose them,
we get the effect of
the definition on
the previous slide.
But much more succinctly,
you'll learn to use
function composition a lot
and not introduce variables
like X in our
previous definition.