Hello. The statements were
introduced in the previous video,
are actually classical statements
introduced into
logic by Aristotle.
And they form what are known
as his categorical propositions.
They say every a is b.
Now ASB, some ASB.
Aristotle was the
first to try and
formalize arguments
using statements.
We saw last time that
in our universe,
every red triangle is small.
And it is not the case that
every small triangle is red.
I want to do here
is to discuss in
a little more detail
how we tell that.
We want to analyze.
How did we decide
that that's the case?
So we're going to look at
every red triangle is small.
And we're going to look at it
in terms of a Venn diagram.
So we're talking here about
the triangles which we've
put inside this circle.
The red things that we
put inside this circle,
and the small things
that we've put
inside this faint circle.
If there were red triangle,
that was not small
way would we find it?
We want to look at
the red triangles.
So the red triangles fall in
this part of the Venn diagram.
So we take the red
triangles and then we
look at the things that is small.
This place here is where we would
put anything that was a
counterexample to this.
Um, because there are
no counter-examples,
it's true that every
red triangle is small.
We can do something similar
for all of the others.
Every small triangle is read it,
every small triangle is red.
Then we take the small
triangles so that
these small triangles
and were true,
we would have found
that this was empty.
We can see that it's
not the case that every
small triangle is right,
because there is
something in here.
And that would have
to be empty to
have every small
triangle being read.
Now we move to the next one.
Some big triangle is amber.
Look now at the big triangles.
They are the things that
are in the triangles,
but not in the small.
So these is the big triangles.
Some big triangle is amber.
Here are the amber things.
And because there is something
in here, this is true.
To show that some began
to triangle is Amber.
We showed that a particular
region is inhabited.
The next one is some
small, this is red.
We then take the small disks.
Here are the disks and
here are the small things.
These are the small
disks, small disk.
And if one of them were red,
this will be inhabited.
But it's not.
So, it's not inhabited.
So this is false.
No red thing is blue
will be our next.
So let's look at the red
things and the blue things.
And to say that no
red thing is blew,
all we need to do is
to say this is empty.
That tells us that no
red thing is blue.
When we looked at these,
we looked at red triangles and
small triangles and big
triangle's small disks.
And we had three predicates
to deal with at once.
But actually, if we think of
red triangle is
a predicate and small
triangle is a predicate.
A big triangle is a predicate
and small disk is a predicate.
Then the kind of reasoning
we've done here with
just two circles will be
enough to check all these
kinds of statement.
And we'll see that next time.