In the last video, we
introduced binary questions.
And now we're going to use
binary questions to form what
are known as decision trees.
We're going to take the
test set as an example.
A chess set has 32 pieces
of 12 different kinds.
There are black and white
pieces, 16 of each.
Within each of those,
there's one came,
one queen, two bishops,
tonight's two looks,
and eight pawns.
So 12 different kinds.
When we come to identify a piece,
the first question
we might ask is,
is it black or white?
If we get the answer, say white,
then we're left with the
remaining six kinds.
Distinguish between nodes.
We can start with the question,
Is it a porn or not upon?
If it's porn, we then done,
and there is not important,
we must decide which of
the five different
kinds there are here,
we have an example of these
are called the minor pieces,
the knights and the bishops.
And these are the major pieces.
So if we ask, is
it major or minor,
then if we get this
answer that it's minor,
that it's either a
night or two Bishop.
So one more question,
we'll finish things.
On the other hand, if
it's major than we
find it's either a
rock or a royal.
If it's Uruk, we're finished.
But if it's a royal, we
must ask one more question.
What we're going to do with
the decision tree is draw
a picture of that process.
Hello, I'm Michael foreman.
We're talking about trees
in the cost quite a lot.
So I thought I would
show you this tree
which is the great sycamore
in Bern and words.
And as you can see,
it has roots which are hidden
launches and it has lease.
And we'll talk about
the way we have roots,
branches, and leaves in our
trees in the next lecture.
Anyway, you should go
and visit Scotland,
unseal it wonderful
things when you have
a chance to come here,
you're not here.
You're missing a lot,
but I hope you're
enjoying yourself,
whatever you want.
Here's the picture.
We start here.
We ask is it upon if it
is, and that's fine.
And if it's not, then
we move to this point.
This symbol here, we readers not.
So it's not a porn.
We come here and we ask,
is it minor or major?
If it's minor, then
just as we said before,
we then have one more question to
determine whether it's
a bishop or a night.
If it's major, we
have that question.
If it's a rook, we're done.
And if it's a royal,
We have one more question to
determine if it's
a queen or again,
so that's very straightforward.
We've introduced negation.
We've introduced the idea of
a tree which will
be very important.
This is the tree.
We call it a tree,
and we call this the root.
We grow our trees
upside down when
we come down anyway following
a branch of the tree.
And when we get to the end,
these things are called leaves.
So we have leaves here,
the root here, the
various branching
points we call nodes.
So a tree has nodes and
edges which are brown,
which form branches going
from the root. To the leaves.
If we now look at this tree,
instead of saying, Is
it minor or major,
we can just ask yes,
no question in each
place so we can say,
is it not upon?
If it's not upon,
we go this way.
If it is upon, and that's false,
that it's not upon.
We go this way.
We asked, is it major?
If it's major, we'd go this way.
If it's minor, in other words
not major, then we go this way.
So depending on whether
it's true or false,
we can go right or left.
Here, instead of asking,
Is it a bishop or a night,
we say, is it a night?
If it is not that it
must be a bishop?
Reduce this decision to a number
of binary questions and in
fact to yes, no question.
The answers now are true
and false at each level.
And if we use 01 as coatings
for true and false,
then we can use this
decision tree to give
a code for each kind of piece.
If we start here, we see a 0.
We go this way.
We've got to porn. If we
see a one, we go this way.
And then if we see
a 0 followed by
a 0, we've got a bishop.
So 1-0-0, Texas to a bishop.
1-0 one takes us to a night,
110 takes us to a rook,
and 1110 takes us to a queen,
and 1111 takes us to the king.
We can take the decision tree
and examine something else.
We can say, how many times
do we ask each question?
How many times do we
ask each question?
If we cover every single
piece in the box,
so we take all the white pieces,
all 16 of them.
For every one, we will
answer this question.
We'll ask, is it a porn or not?
If it's not, there are
eight things which are not.
And we ask, are there
major or minor?
We divide those into the
minor and the major.
So we ask this question
before, this question, before.
After that, we've
determined these two,
but we still ask
the question again.
If we get a royal,
so twice we ask this
question, is it a k?
So there are eight things for
which you ask one question.
There are six things for
which we ask 123 questions.
And there are two things for
which we ask 1234 questions.
We sum that up,
then we've got a total of 34.
And that's the same as
adding up the numbers
that I put inside these nodes.
So this is the code presented
as a decision tree.
It encodes each piece
as a series of bits,
which is either one bit 0,
or in these cases three bits,
or in this case, these
cases four bits.
It's a variable length encoding.
In the next video,
we'll look at alternative
encodings that don't require
so many questions to
determine whether
it's a king or queen.