In the last video,
we presented this
decision tree as a way of
discovering with
yes-no questions which
of the white pieces we're
looking at from a chess set?
This decision tree corresponds
to a variable length encoding of
the kinds of piece
using codes that are
13 or four bits long.
What we're going to do now is to
go in the opposite direction.
We're going to start with
the code and then draw
the decision tree.
So we're going to look
at another encoding.
If we have three binary bits,
then we can represent
every number from 0,
which is 000, to seven,
which is 111 altogether,
that's eight numbers.
We can represent
eight different patterns
with three bits.
We can choose six of
those patterns to represent
our kinds of piece.
If we look at this encoding,
we can also picture
it as a Venn diagram.
We can say the code is a, b, c,
where the first bit,
the second bit and
the third bit are a,
B, and C. A is the one.
If the first bit is one,
that's if we have
a rock or a royal.
So here we have a rock or a roil,
That's a V For the
second bit is one.
If we have a bishop or a royal,
B is a bishop or a royal bit,
c is the last bit.
That's true.
If we have a knight or a king,
that it's night or Cain,
the porn has no bit set.
So the point is encoded by zeros
00 and falls outside
all of the circles.
This band diagram
has eight regions.
These two empty regions
are codes we haven't used.
This one is 101 and
this one is 011.
And if you look at it or find
those patents that are
missing from this list,
we take that encoding.
We can again think
of asking questions,
but now the questions will
be based on the first bit.
Is it true or is it false?
Is it true, or is it false?
On the second bit? Is it true
or is it false, and so on.
So we fill that in.
0.0.0 gives us the pole.
001 gives us the night.
One. 0-0 gives us the rock.
And 110 gives us a queen.
111 gives us the king.
That straightforward,
just mapping
the code back to a tree.
Now if we take a tree and
try and view it as
a decision tree,
then we don't need
to make a decision
here because by the time
we get to this point,
the only place we can end up
here with the bishop over here,
we've drawn the tree
again, but this time.
Cutting these decisions because
we don't need to
ask any questions
that we know that if
it's a proper code
by this stage will have a
bishop or we'll have a look.
We can put the questions
in. At the top.
We ask the question which
is true for these three.
That is true.
If we have a major piece
that we ask, is it major?
Then we ask, is it royal?
If it's not roil, it's a rock.
If it is royal than we
ask, is this a king?
And if it's not a
king than its queen,
if it wasn't major,
that we ask, is it a bishop?
If it's not a bishop than
we ask, is it night?
If it's not a night than
we find that it is upon.
So this accomplishes
the same task.
It manages to take any piece
and answer a number of yes,
no questions and tell
us what piece it is.
And you might think
this is better
because here we answer
the question about
the king and queen with
three questions instead of
four with our previous encoding.
But every now count the number
of questions will ask you
reclassified every piece in
the set or every white
piece in the set.
Then we start off
here with 16 pieces.
The major pieces
malaria four of them.
So forego this way.
The remaining 12 go here.
And we then ask, is it a
bishop that uses two of them?
So they're maintaining go here.
And for these ten, we
ask, is it a night?
Two of them are nice,
but the rest a poems
and end up here.
So we have eight points,
two nights through bishops
to kings and as before,
one queen among cane.
And for the bishop and the ROCC,
we ask two questions.
So there are four of
them with two questions.
For the rest, we
asked three questions
and there are 12 of them
with three questions.
And then read that together.
That's 36 plus eight
is 44 questions.
So comparing that with what
we did in the previous video,
we find that in the
previous video we had
this decision tree which asked
34 questions when presented
with all the pieces.
And this time we have
this decision tree which
asks 44 questions you who
presented with all of them.
If we're going to get
randomly given pieces,
randomly with the frequencies
that they occur in chess.
Then this is
a more efficient decision
tree than this one.
Here a couple of
questions for you to
do after you've finished
looking at the video.
The first one is
just a general
question to which you
will learn the answer if
you don't know it already.
And you really need to have
this answer ingrained in
your head eventually.
So with three bits,
we can encode eight values.
We encoded six values
using three bits book
that left us with
two spec codes that we
could've encoded up
to eight values.
How many bits do we need
to encode n values,
where n is any positive number?
And here's a hint.
What's the binary
representation of 42?
How many bits do we
need to code 42 values?
If you don't know the
answer, you'll need
to answer this question.
Look at it carefully and then
see how you derive this number.
Another question is, how
many different
encodings are there?
So we'll look at the simplest
example of that question.
Well, the simplest
interesting example is always
encoding to values with one bit.
There are two ways to do it.
You can decide which one's
true and which one false,
or you can swap them over.
But with three values
we need two bits.
How many ways are
there of encoding
three values using two bits?
Here are two of the ways.
You can check that
the calculation given on
the left gives us
all of the ways.
And now, how many
ways are there of
encoding six values
using three bits,
which is what we just did.
I leave that for you.