Let's just think a
bit about things.
We're going to look
at collections of
things to keep it simple.
We're going to look at
finite collections of
things and things
have properties.
So here we've got some cosmetics.
One of the important properties
of cosmetics is that colour.
There will be plenty of
other important properties.
We have some tools,
these tools that
dimensions are going to be
very important and
maybe their weight.
These crayons, well,
color's important,
but again, there are other
properties that are important.
This crockery, the
wake, is important.
The look of them is important.
The other examples
on this page are
examples of games in
one way or another.
Here we have a croquet set,
a set of weights for
exercising models,
mythical beasts, and a chess set.
I want to talk a little bit
about these different
kinds of gaining,
the Cronkite said, as
balls and mallets.
And it's important
that the balls have
their particular
dimensions and weights
that the hoop sat there
particular dimensions.
It's important that
the mallets or true
and have flat faces with
which to hit the balls.
For the weights, the
weights are important,
the dimensions of the
bars important for these,
the physical properties are
really essential to these items.
If I now coming here,
the mythical beasts are
somewhat different.
They representations of
things that don't exist.
So here we have a flying horse.
And I can ask you questions
about the flying horse,
how many witnesses attack?
And you can look and
count the wings.
But if I ask you,
what's its blood temperature?
You're gonna get me a Scotland's.
Well, it doesn't have blood.
The model doesn't have blood.
Actually the mythical horse does,
because a mythical horse
can bleed to death,
but its temperature
doesn't make sense.
These mythical beasts,
you have the properties
that we ascribe to them.
Or at least the myth
makers ascribe to them.
They have those properties
and it doesn't make
sense to ask about
other properties.
Strangely, this bird has
red and orange wings.
So this is a mythical beast with
a physical representation
of the color of its wings.
And it's a physical
representation
of the color that only
exists in a myth.
And we can recognize it
because we know what
red looks like.
The chess set is in some
ways the most interesting.
The chess pieces.
Represent individual
capabilities.
So the way that
the king can move,
the way that the queen can move,
the ways they can
take other pieces,
the actions they can take differ.
And there's no representation of
those properties directly in
the way they are modeled.
And we could model them
quite differently and
still recognize this
as a chess set.
They do have laws that
govern the ways they may move
on the board and the
things they can do.
Do we need a board to play chess?
While some people down, there are
people who can play
testing their heads.
And certainly a computer
can play chess without
the Jess said.
In some sense, it
plays virtually.
So what is logic?
Logic has something in
common with this example.
On something in common
with this example,
less in common with
the weights on the CR.
Okay? In the case of
the mythical beasts,
we have mythical creatures
which exist only
virtually and which
have the properties
that the myth makers
of given them.
And then we'd make
a physical model.
In logic, we often take
a physical situation and
then we abstract from
that physical situation and make
virtual things or mythical things
if you want to put it that way,
which had only the properties
that we've focused on.
And we ignore all the
other properties.
And now we reason about
those properties in
just the same way as we would
reason about the properties
of the mythical beasts.
Logic also has something in
common with the chess example.
Because as well as
modeling properties
of some abstract things that
only have those properties,
we can model the capabilities
of those things,
the ways they can interact,
the ways they can move
on a virtual board.
But instead of it
being a virtual board,
we can make a model that
follows some rules,
rather like the rules of chess.
A reason about the real world
by actually reasoning
about the model.
In this video, we've
introduced the discussion of
the relationship between
logic, models and reality.
In the case of the mythical
beasts and the class pieces,
we have some ideas
of properties of
the bees or capabilities
of the chess pieces.
And we use physical marbles
to represent those.
And to help us to visualize
the mythical beasts and
the abstract capabilities
of the chess pieces.
What we're going to
go with logic is to
get a language that
allows us to take
real situations and create
virtual situations.
That model. Some of
their properties.
If we choose the properties we
model appropriately, we can,
we can make our models both
tractable in the
sense that we can
use computers to play games
represented by those models.
And applicable in the sense that
the results of those games
were mirrored in the real world.
You can use chess as
a metaphor to try
and understand this.
Logic allows us to convert
many real-world problems
into gains a bit like chess,
we use symbols to replace
the various entities involved
and describe their interactions.
And computers play these
games to solve real problems.
We'll also use computers
to help us do logic.
You don't need a computer,
but the computer can
help you to learn
logic just as a chessboard.
Even a virtual chess board
can help you to learn chess.
So we'll be using Haskell
to help you learn logic.
Really. Yeah.