So remember I said the difference
between functional programs
is that they're not Tikki,
Tikki, Tikki, that
they are whoosh.
And right, you've seen
some Tikki Tikki
operations on numbers.
You've seen some
wash doing things
with whole pictures at a time.
But you didn't see
how to do that yet.
I said, Oh, that's,
that's abstract.
Don't worry about
it. That's a detail
you don't need to know yet.
So here for the first time,
I'm going to show you how to
build large data structures from
small ones and how to operate
woosh on that whole
structure at once.
So the large data structure
that's built out of
small ones is called the list.
And the thing that
operates on it is
called a list comprehension.
And you can go to
the webpage for the
reading list, okay, lists.
So wait, now I think
I can do a demo.
Let's try this.
Just checking to see
what I want to demo.
Okay. Wait, now I
have to do that.
To do that.
I have to do at this.
Doo Doo Doo Doo Doo Doo
Doo
Doo Doo
Doo Doo Doo Doo Doo Doo
Doo Doo Doo Doo Doo Doo.
Do, do, do, do, do, do what?
Catherine amendment. You
like my singing, right?
Doo Doo Doo Doo Doo Doo
Doo Doo Doo, Doo, Doo Doo.
You don't need any of those.
Yeah. Okay, here's a file.
So my list is going to
be a list of integers.
And my list is gonna
consist of the favorite integers
of the people in this route.
Your favorite integer is
Forty-two, same as mine.
Your favorite integer
is next person.
12. Next prison.
35. Next person, seven.
Let's be consistent.
Seven, next person thought,
and somebody likes 100, okay?
So there's a list, right?
Good. And here we're
executing things.
So if I type, I go into it.
You might use Haskell
in different ways.
You can use your favorite editor.
My favorite editor
is called Emacs.
I'm typing the program here.
And then when I type
control C, control l,
It gives me an
execution window here.
And in fact, let's just kill
them for a minute. Go back.
See. Right. So it
begins by saying, hi,
you're running G
HCI. What does DHC?
I stand for Glasgow Haskell
Compiler interactive.
So in fact, the main compiler for
Haskell is called the
Glasgow Haskell Compiler.
It's now maintained by
Simon Peyton Jones,
who's a research
senior researcher
at Microsoft Research
in Cambridge.
But he and I used
to be colleagues at
Glasgow University on the
other side of the country.
And that's where
this was first done.
So that's why it's called the
Glasgow Haskell Compiler,
Scottish heritage for
functional programming.
And what's said, okay, I'm ready,
JC, I've loaded the prelude.
That's a bunch of
definitions that you
normally get by default.
It's called the Prelude.
And that says, okay,
one module loaded,
meaning I actually read
the Prelude and it worked.
And oh sorry, noted,
the module load is made,
so it's given a name
to this file here.
I didn't write down the name.
So choosing the name
main, it says, okay,
one module loaded, meaning this,
sorry, not meaning the prelude.
It always loads the Prelude.
And now I've got these
definitions in so I can say,
what is the type, so
containings, What is the typeof?
You can also say, you can
also spell it this
way, doesn't matter.
And says, yep, that's
a list of integers,
which is exactly
what I said here.
And now I get asked things
about like what is my list?
Okay, it's what we thought.
I can say. What is the
length of my list?
What's it going to
say? Six, right,
because they six numbers
written down there.
Or I can say what is
the sum of my list?
And it will say 201. Or I
can even say what is the product?
Product of my list?
And it gives us a big number.
Let's see. So count up to en.
He's going to take a
list of integers, sorry,
it's going to take an
integer and give us a list
of integers from one
up to that number.
Well-defined count
up of n as the list.
That's the numbers from
one to n, c, thats right.
Though I did something wrong.
Yeah, I need to put brackets
around this downtime.
Wow, I've forgotten how Haskell
works. That's impressive.
No luck.
I'm now going to program
the way you all program.
Bring up the browser.
Factorial in Haskell.
Yep. Yep, it Is that okay.
What am I getting wrong?
Oh, that's what I did
wrong. Thank you.
Write its count, takes
an integer and returns
a list of integer.
Of course. There we go.
Yay. So now I can say
cout for count up.
Write. Short. Names are better.
Not everybody agrees
with that advice,
but we don't want
that. There we go.
Cout for 1234.
Count ten, 1-2-3-4-5, 1042.
Length count 42.
Factorial product.
Count 42.
Big number. Await this wrong.
Actually, I want to
do that's possibly the Nau
didn't get an overflow.
Ok. You can also say integer.
Then you get really big numbers.
So it's reloaded it.
Right? Yeah, I see that.
That oh, wow.
Right. This is bad.
I don't know why that happen.
It gave the wrong answer.
I didn't say anything.
It should have said,
this is a bigger number
than will fit in an int.
And given what's called
an overflow error.
But it did not,
I don't know why it didn't give
an overflow error it
should have done.
I do some work with
crypto currencies.
It turns out that
literally tens of millions
of US dollars been
lost through overflow areas
that were not detected.
So never designed something
that doesn't detect
overflow errors and that should
detect an overflow
error. That's very bad.
But using integers we can
see we can get represent
very long numbers
inside the computer.
So even the numbers
are not really Tikki,
Tikki, they're
actually represented.
They can be represented as a
single word in the computer,
but they are sometimes
represented as
multiple words represent
very long numbers like this.
Okay, so now we're
going to go back to the
lecture for a minute.
Remind myself what I
was going to cover.
So we can make lists of
things that are characters.
And in fact, here I've made
a list of characters I NF-1,
but that's just the
same as this strings.
You can write a single
character between
single quotes or a list
of characters called a string
between double quotes.
We can also have lists of lists,
of lists of functions
that act on pictures.
You can't have lists of
things of different types.
Alright, and we've seen count.
So now we can do
list comprehensions.
So let's do some examples.
So let's define square.
So that takes an
integer to an integer.
And it will define the square
of x is just x times x.
So now I can do
something like I want to
square every x for
x from one to ten.
Oh, I forgot to load
it. Try that again.
And there were the squares
of the first ten numbers.
And I want to find the
sum of the squares,
the first ten numbers.
That's 385, right?
And we could sum the squares
of the numbers up to n.
Not happy. I want the formal
parameter to be n not x.
So x appears here.
So x is called a variable,
n is called a variable.
This n is a formal parameter.
This X is an actual
parameter to square.
Whereas here x is the
formal parameter.
Of course, I can use
any names I want
as long as I use
them consistently.
That doesn't have to
be X, it could be y.
So now let's check that we get
the same answer
before we got 385.
Sum the squares of
the numbers up to
ten, and you get 385.
If you'd hope. So
let's do squares.
So that will take a list of
integer and give us
a list of integer.
So we're just gonna square
every number in the list.
So how would I write that?
So first I need a formal
parameter for a list.
By convention.
If x ranges over integers,
I'll use X S, two range
over list of integers.
That's just a convention.
You can give it
any name you want.
You can call it Fred.
Well, I'm going to
call an excess.
That's a nice convention,
but don't use it to access.
So square of x for x
drawn from excess.
So now I can say squares of
the numbers from one to ten,
I gets the same thing as before.
Another cool thing I can
do is just pick out some
numbers from a list.
So here I'm going to take
a list up odds.
So od is defined in Haskell.
It's part of the prelude.
What do you think that lips,
what do you think
that's going to return?
True? Because three is odd.
What's that going to return?
False. 0 is even.
So odds of xs is equal to,
I'm just gonna return x. Whoops.
For each x drawn from
xs such that x is odd.
So this will give us all the
odd numbers in the list.
I better do load it. So now od.
This gives us, whoa, odds.
Thanks. And that gives
us all the odd
numbers between 110.
And then if I want to find
the squares of the odd
numbers from one to ten,
I could do squares, odds.
Or of course I could
do odds squares.
1210. Oops, but it
helps if I spelled
correctly, it doesn't, it?
Will that be the same?
Let's find out who it's the same.
What a funny coincidence.
Why is it the same?
Yep. Because right.
So if you square an odd number,
you get an odd number.
Exactly. And so that's why
either of these happened to
give you the same answer.
Generally, the order in which you
do these is very important.
In this particular
case, it is not.
Ok. What was my next thing to do?
Right? So now we
can also put these together
and do them all at once.
So you can build
big things out of
little things or just do
all the work at once.
So actually let's
do one more thing.
Let's find the sum of
the squares of the odd
numbers from one to ten.
That happens to be a 165.
But we could do some square odd.
I'll take a list of
integers and give
us just one integer.
Sum square odd of xs will be,
I'm, I'm tired of typing Xs.
I'm going to type Fred this time.
Sum square audits.
Fred will be the sum of the
squares of the odds of Fred.
And I can do sum square on
a Fred. But no, no, no.
Fred is the formal
parameter here.
I'm going to give an actual
parameter of one to ten.
Or I can give it
different actual prime.
I can give it my list.
Okay? So if you sum the square of
all the odd numbers
there, you get 1299.
So notice there's a property
that expect to hold here.
So remember I said do it twice.
So let's do it twice.
Here's a property
of sum square odd.
So I'm gonna give this
a list of integers.
I'm going to check
that a property holds.
And what's my property?
So I'm going to use a
variable name here.
Let's use Fred. And
the property I want is
some square odd of Fred
should be the same as,
the same as is written
as two equal signs.
Some of the squares
of the odds of Fred.
Okay? And let's just
check that that's true.
Does this property hold
for the list1 to ten?
Okay, it's true.
Does it hold for
the list? My list?
Gay, it's true.
Oh, let's make up lots of
random numbers and just lots
of random list and try
it for all of them.
So now I need to import
a module called test
dot quick check.
Works. Yep, and now I
can say QuickCheck.
Prop sum, square od.
Okay. Passed 100 tests.
So it made up a live,
a 100 different lists, integers.
And it tried it on all of them.
And every single
time it got true.
To see if I've got an example
where it gets thoughts.
So to naming some names
for these things,
this is pronounced drawn from
and X drawn from one to three
is called the generator.
The arrow is called drawn from.
When you white some
condition here,
it could be odd of x, it
could be x greater than 0.
It could be a character
is alphanumeric.
That's called a guard.
We've already seen how to do
factorial and we've
seen some square Odds.
We've seen QuickCheck.
Alright, I wanted
to tell you very
briefly because
you'll need it for,
not this week's tutorial,
but next week's tutorial.
There are three
functions on lists.
Had it gives you
the first element,
tail gives you everything
but the first element,
the single colon is pronounced
Cons, short for construct.
And it just puts
a thing at the very
beginning of the list.
So one put at the
beginning of the list
to three, gives you 123.
And then here's a
property we could check.
Given a list of integers,
either it should be
the empty list, right?
You can take the head or
tail of an empty list.
So either it should
be the empty list
or, oops, that's misspelled.
That should be
spelled vertical bar.
Vertical bar had x's colon
tail xs is equal to xs.
We can try that one out.
You know, there we go.
So there's the property.
Let's make this
screen what there?
So I wrote or in the
slide, I will fix it.
It should be double vertical bar.
And I can run this road
one mA and now again,
I can do the same thing.
Quick. Check. Prop head, tail.
Okay, passed 100 tests.
Knows if I got it wrong,
it can help me find it right.
It's very important to
remember or you can't
take head or tail
of the empty list.
So what if I leave this
out and do it again?
Failed falsifiable
after one test.
Doesn't work for the empty list.
Okay, so what have we learn?
Number is Tikki, Tikki,
Tikki lists, list comprehensions.
Rush. Do it twice.
The computer can help
you check that what you've
done is consistent,
that the property, if you
believe, should hold,
do whole and can
reveal errors for you.