Hi, my name's Phil Wadler,
and this is the introduction to
the introduction to computation,
which is Informatics1A.
This is Lecture Zero.
You'll find out why it's
Lecture Zero later in the course.
So let's begin by
talking about who.
Hi, I'm Philip Wadler.
I'm the lecturer for the
functional programming
part of the course,
and I am also the Course Head.
There's my email and
my office number.
The email will do you some good,
the office number less so.
This is Michael Fourman.
He's the lecturer
for the computation
and logic part of the course,
and he's left a wee message for you.
I'm here to blow away
the cobwebs while
preparing for the start of term,
Fresher's week
next week and looking forward
to seeing you all here.
This is Edinburgh.
This is Arthur's Seat.
Magnificent.
Plenty of wind,
so the air's clean and plenty of
natural vegetation when
you're outside. Now I'm sorry
I won't be inside
with you for awhile.
But we're going to
do things online
and I'm looking
forward to meeting
you all next week.
Thank you, Michael.
This is Claudia Chirita.
She is the teaching assistant
for the course.
She's been doing a
huge amount to help
getting everything ready,
among other things.
She's responsible for
putting up the material on
Learn where you will
be accessing it.
This is Don Sannella.
He is another professor at
the University of Edinburgh,
just like Michael and myself.
He used to teach on
this course and he
spent his sabbatical
writing a textbook for you
based on the material
in this course.
And we'll have more about
that textbook a bit later.
This is Heather Yorston.
She gives a set of
optional lectures,
Mathematics for Computing.
These will be available
pre recorded,
just like the lectures
from Michael and myself.
Lectures from Michael and me will
be required for you to listen to.
Hers are optional in case you
want more background
in mathematics,
which is very useful.
If you don't have
a strong background, then
these lectures are
there to help you out.
And everybody on the
course will, of course,
help you out with any
questions you have
about mathematics
or anything else.
This is Perdita Stevens.
She's the author of a textbook
'How to Write Good Programs',
which among other things,
is aimed at this course,
so you might want to
get that textbook.
I'll say more about
textbooks later.
She's served as a tutor on
this course for many years.
She's an excellent tutor and
she's going to be helping
me this year to supervise
the online tutorials.
More on that later too.
This is Paul Anderson.
He's in charge of all of the
Informatics1
first-year courses.
So he's in charge
of the entire year.
This is Laura Ambrose.
She works in the Informatics
Teaching Organization
and she's responsible
for the administrative side
of the course.
If you need to do
something like change the
time of your tutorial,
she is the person to speak to.
So all of these
emails are here, these
slides will be
online via Learn,
so it'll be easy for you to
get this information.
Let me tell you a bit about Where.
I mentioned the Informatics
Teaching Organization.
So let's explain things.
Here's the Informatics Forum.
This is where Michael
and I have offices.
Here's Appleton Tower.
This is where the ITO is located.
Of course, given circumstances,
you might not go to
these things at all.
But I'm showing you where they
are in case that's helpful.
And another thing
I'll show you is
right here's the general area.
Here's the Informatics Forum.
Here's Appleton Tower.
And up here is Blackwells Bookshop.
I just happened to be in there
yesterday. So here's Blackwells
Bookshop. Bookshops
are an amazing thing.
The web and Amazon
is killing them off,
but there's still
an amazing thing.
Among other things, you
might want a physical book.
If you do, I encourage
you to get it
from Blackwells or some
other physical bookshop.
Of course, you can get it
online as well if you prefer.
And in fact, these are
the computing shelves
at Blackwells. Always
worth a visit.
And part of those shelves,
here are the textbooks
available for the course
if you want them.
And I'll say a bit
more about that.
So what are the textbooks
for the course?
So first and foremost,
there is the new textbook
that Don Sanella has written.
There will be forums
available for feedback via Learn.
Your feedback is very much
encouraged to help make this
even better for
students next year.
This is our first year trialing
out this new textbook.
There's some other textbooks
that we've used in the past.
One is 'Haskell, the craft of
functional programming'
by Simon Thompson.
And another is Learn You a
Haskell for Great Good.
By Miran Lipovaca.
They're both available
as physical books and
Learn You a Haskell is also
available for free online.
So you might want
to check those out.
Whatever resource
is helpful to you,
I urge you to get. Textbooks,
if it's physical cost money.
Sometimes they cost, you know,
they cost 50 pounds,
which seems like a
huge amount of money.
But if you think about what
the Scottish government invest in
the students here for
one years course,
50 pounds is nothing.
If you need to spend 50
pounds to make good use...
of the course, of the opportunities
available through the course,
that is a bargain.
So I encourage you
to consider it.
And if you think it's
helpful, go ahead and do it.
Here's how to write
good programs.
Perdita's book, which
I mentioned before.
This is not a textbook
for the course per se,
but has lots of advice about how
to write good programs,
including Haskell programs,
which is what we're going to be
doing in the functional
programming part of the course.
And Haskell will also play
an important role in
the computation and logic
part of the course.
So again, check this book
out. If it's helpful for you,
I encourage you to get it.
How? So we're going to have
lectures, pre recorded, each week.
There will be
roughly two hours of
functional programming
lectures recorded by myself,
two hours of computation
and logic lectures
recorded by Michael Fourman.
The functional programming
lectures are mainly going
to be those recorded last year.
That's because I think I work
better with an audience.
I think you will enjoy
better those things
recorded with an audience.
Michael has decided to take
advantage of the new
world, while your in,
and he's going to be doing
the computation
and logic lectures
in a different style.
We're all learning
as we move forward.
I thought the best
thing to give you is
pre-recorded lectures
from last year.
We'll see how that goes.
Everybody on the course,
including Michael and myself,
will be soliciting feedback
from you as the course proceeds.
Now, we really want to
encourage you to
view these lectures.
So for the FP part of the course,
there's going to be a quiz
each week based on the lectures.
And for the CL part,
there's going to be a test
every other week based on the
material in the lectures.
But, and this is
really important:
Lectures are not enough.
Where you're going to do
most of the learning.
I am sad to say, is not
through me talking at you,
saying wonderful
bits of knowledge.
You learn things by doing them.
And your opportunity
to do things and
get feedback is the tutorials.
So we're going to have a one hour
live tutorial each week for
functional programming.
We're going to have
a 1.5 hour live
tutorial each week for
computation and logic.
These are done in large groups
and then subgroups of six.
These are done in groups of ten.
You will have a tutor assigned to
you who you can go
to for feedback.
So this is really important.
So we've got a tutorial that
you must do each week for
FP, and a tutorial each
that you must do each week
for computation and logic.
There are also live
demonstrations every
weekday from just after four
o'clock to five o'clock.
These are not required,
but they're optional.
But again, there's a live
demonstrated there who can
deal with your questions.
They're are a good place
to go to get help.
Another good place to go
to get help is Piazza.
You can put up questions
at anytime and
any other student and
the staff will put up
answers to those questions.
It's a very effective
means of getting feedback.
Another very important
effective means of getting
feedback is your
colleagues, your peers.
There is InfPALS,
which has people in
successive years who've
been through this course.
You can go to them for feedback
or just make friends
on the course,
talk to other people,
work with other people.
It's very much encouraged
that you use every resource
available from the staff
through to other
students to learn.
It's important that
you do the work.
Attendance at tutorials
is compulsory,
it is not optional.
You must listen to the
lectures each week,
before the tutorial.
You must do the assigned
reading each week
that will be available on
Learn before the tutorial.
You must do the
tutorial exercises
each week before the tutorial.
And that is so important
that if I was live,
I would be jumping
up and down to tell
you how important that
is, but I'm not live,
I can't really jump up and down.
So instead of that,
what I've got here is a
little dancing teddy bear.
And he is dancing and
jumping up and down.
Very angry to tell you just how
important it is that
you do the work.
So I'm just going to repeat this.
You wouldn't think I
need to repeat it.
But experience shows students
believe that they can get
away for some
reason without doing this,
I already mentioned just
how much money is
given by the Scottish government
to ensure these resources
are available to you.
So really it's very
important that you use them.
You must listen to
the lectures each week
before the tutorial.
You must do the assigned reading
each week before the tutorial,
you must do the tutorial exercises
each week before the tutorial.
You may collaborate.
When you are doing these things,
especially this
tutorial exercises,
you're encouraged to collaborate.
As I said, other
students are resource.
It's all too easy if you're
working with another student
who's stronger than you to
let them do all the work.
But you have to submit
your own answers.
You are responsible for
knowing the material.
If you copy somebody
else's work directly,
that is cheating. Don't do that.
But working with other students
to learn, that's fine.
And again, let me
state the obvious.
You will fail the course
if you don't do the work.
That's in italics
to emphasize it.
And here's the teddy bear
to emphasize that as well.
Now, to encourage you to do this,
the weave, all of
the work that I just mentioned
is going to be assessed.
So you have a reason to do it.
You know that you're getting
points for doing it.
So there's a 100
marks for the course.
50 of those are for
functional programming,
computation and logic.
To pass the course,
you must pass each
of those separately.
You must get 20 out of 50 marks
in each of those to pass.
So here, the 50 marks for FP,
there's a quiz each week worth 1 piint.
There's a tutorial each week,
which will be marked by your
tutor worth four points.
There is a mid-term
also worth four points.
It will be essentially like
a tutorial and marked
by your tutor.
And there will be a final, again,
it's four points,
essentially like a tutorial.
The midterm and
the final are there.
You can see they're a relatively
small part of the assessment,
but they are there to
give you feedback.
As I mentioned, you
might be working with
other students to
do the tutorials.
Don't work with other students
to do the midterm or the final,
that will give you some feedback
on what you've learned.
Now if you add these up,
you see we've got 40 points,
sorry, ten points here.
One times 10, 4 times ten
is 40, plus 10 is 50.
But then we've got another
four points for the midterm,
four points for the final.
But of these 12 items,
you will be scored on
the best 10 of 12.
So if you miss a
tutorial one week
or do very poorly on
something for some reason,
that won't count
as long as you do
well enough on the rest.
For computation and logic,
the assessment is
a bit different.
There is a test every other
week worth four points,
and a tutorial each
week worth two points,
and then a final
worth ten points,
and those add up to
exactly 50. I should say,
and then on Learn,
so all the resources that you
need will be published on Learn,
including the video that
you're watching right now for me,
all of our pre recorded
video lectures
will be available on Learn.
All the slides will
be available on
Learn, all the
reading assignments,
all the tutorial assignments.
Once they're done,
all the solutions,
everything will be
put up on Learn.
There'll be a programming
competition for
FP later this year that will be
posted on Learn. Everything you
need, the link to the piazza site,
everything will be
available on Learn.
Let me say a word about When.
So this is the actual timetable.
It actually has lectures as
specific time in it right now.
We're going to remove
that because you
can see the Lectures
anytime you want.
Very important, right?
These are the demonstrations
which I mentioned,
which will be every weekday
four o'clock to five o'clock,
live, great place
to get feedback.
There will also be office hours.
Michael will have one
office hour each week.
I will have an office
hour each week.
When those hours to be decided,
that will be posted on Learn.
A lot of things are
probably going to
change as the course
goes forward.
Because this is new to all of us.
And we're hoping to
get feedback from
you on what works
and what doesn't.
Piazza and e-mail will be
great ways of delivering
that feedback.
So things will change.
Again, it will be very important.
Look at Learn, that
we'll always have the
most up to date information.
One thing I should mention
about the tutorials.
You can see that
the computation and
logic tutorials will be near
the beginning of the week,
probably all on Monday.
The FP tutorials
will all be near
the end of the week,
probably on Friday.
I believe what we're going
to do is have a Wednesday
four o'clock deadline for the
FP tutorials on Friday.
And that will give your
tutors time to mark them.
Again, this will all be on Learn.
And the CL work will
also have a deadline,
but that's yet to be decided.
It will be on Learn.
Finally, Why. Right, you
want to know a little bit about
why we're doing all this.
But I'm not going to cover that
in the introductory lecture.
I, Michael and I will
be covering the Why of
functional programming
part of the course
and the computation and
logic part of the course
at the beginning of
our first lectures,
which you will see,
which will be available
to you online.
But I will just give you a hint.
It has something to do
with the lambda calculus.
Here is my fuzzy lambda
that was made as a little
warm, fuzzy toy for
me by my daughter.
And you'll learn more
about fuzzy lambdas
later in the course.
That's it. That's the
introduction completed.
Welcome! to Introduction to
Computation Informatics1A.
This has been the
Introduction to
the Introduction to
Computation. Go well.